<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<document
   xmlns="https://iead.ittl.gtri.org/wr24/doc/2011-09-30-2258"
   xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
   xmlns:appinfo="http://release.niem.gov/niem/appinfo/3.0/"
   xmlns:doc="https://iead.ittl.gtri.org/wr24/doc/2011-09-30-2258"
   xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#"
   xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
   xmlns:structures="http://release.niem.gov/niem/structures/3.0/"
   xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
 

   <title>National Information Exchange Model <char name="mdash"/> High-Level Version Architecture</title>
   <version>3.0</version>
   <date>2015-04-27</date>
   <author>NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC)</author>

   <image src="img/niem-logo-sm.png"/>

   <subsection><title>URI</title>
	<p><strong><link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/high-level-version-architecture/3.0/</link></strong></p>
   </subsection>


  <subsection><title>Contents</title>
  	<tableOfContents/>
  </subsection>


  <subsection><title>Abstract</title>
	<p>This document specifies the National Information Exchange Model (NIEM) version architecture.  This specification identifies the processes, artifacts, responsibilities and how they interact to produce new releases of and updates to the NIEM model.  This draft establishes a regular schedule for <termRef term="major release">major</termRef> and <termRef term="minor release">minor releases</termRef> per the new Release Optimization Strategy (approved by the NIEM Executive Steering Council in June 2014).</p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection><title>Status</title>
	  <p>This document defines the design for versioning that evolved from the collaborative work of the NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), and subsequent work of the NIEM Business Architecture Committee (NBAC).  The Release Optimization Strategy is a recommendation to the Executive Steering Council (ESC) to allow a regular annual <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> as needed.  In June 2014 the ESC approved the recommendation.  <ref idref="NIEM-HLVA3"/> supersedes the previous <ref idref="NIEM-HLVA1"/> dated 31 July 2008.</p>
    	<p>This specification is a product of the NIEM Program Management Office (PMO).</p>
    	<p>Email comments on this specification to <link href="mailto:niem-comments%40lists.gatech.edu?subject=NIEM%20MPD%20Specification%20Version%203.0">niem-comments@lists.gatech.edu</link>.</p>
</subsection>


<section id="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>

	<p>This document describes the National Information Exchange Model (NIEM) version architecture at a high level.  It describes the approach and the major artifacts involved, without specifying them at a detailed level.  This document is intended to frame further discussion and specification efforts, leading to a precise specification in the future.</p>

	<p>The version architecture discusses issues that have inherently conflicting tradeoffs.  It seeks a balance of concepts drawn from previous NTAC discussions and ideas.  Major tradeoffs include:</p>

<ul>
	<li><p>Timeliness versus stability</p></li>
	<li><p>Domain autonomy versus interoperability</p></li>
	<li><p>Ease for information exchange package documentation (IEPD) developers versus ease for <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> developers</p></li>
</ul>


<section id="Scope"><title>Scope</title>
	
	<p>The HLVA describes how <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef> updates the data components and schema documents that comprise a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  This document is a high-level, abstract form of the eventual specification.  It describes, at a high level, topics that will be specified by a complete version architecture.</p> 

	<p>This specification does not address version management for information exchange package documentation (IEPD).  Creation and management of IEPDs is the responsibility of NIEM stakeholders and developers, and processes for IEPD versioning and management are independent of NIEM core and domains.  The NIEM PMO defines IEPD conformance, but IEPD development, management, and implementation fall outside its scope.  Nonetheless, in the near term the PMO intends to publish guidance (through the NIEM Technical Architecture Committee) for managing IEPDs, versioning IEPDs, and processing their associated information exchange packages (IEP).</p>
			
	<p>This document assumes that the reader is familiar with NIEM and its artifacts.  Readers needing additional background on NIEM should refer to documents on the NIEM Web site at <link>http://reference.niem.gov/</link>.</p>

</section>


<section id="Background"><title>Background</title>

	<p>The NIEM is represented as a set of XML Schema documents that define data components.  Implementers of information exchange package documentation (IEPD) use these data components to define information exchange packages (IEP) that will be transmitted in an implementation.  The goal of NIEM is to define common data components that are highly reusable, to improve the economy of implementing information exchanges, to increase comprehension of those exchanges, and to reduce errors in exchanges.</p>

	<p>The NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC) and the NIEM Business Architecture Committee (NBAC) govern NIEM architecture and content respectively.  The NBAC and NTAC may appoint standing subcommittees and transitory tiger teams who take responsibility for specific <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef>.  NTAC and NBAC make technical recommendations to the NIEM Program Management Office (PMO).  The PMO is the operational body that directs and executes NIEM daily operations, development, maintenance, and public relations.  The Executive Steering Council (ESC) is the senior executive level group that reviews and approves major NIEM directions and activities.</p>

	<definition term="NIEM governance">
		<p>The aggregation of the Executive Steering Council (ESC), the NIEM Program Management Office (PMO), the NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), and the NIEM Business Architecture Committee (NBAC).</p>
	</definition>

	<p>The NIEM content model is intentionally partitioned into specialized <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> under <termRef>NIEM core</termRef>.</p>

	<definition term="NIEM core">
		<p>The content of a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> that is common or universal to all (or almost all) <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="NIEM domain">
		<p>A partition of a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> that represents specialized data requirements for a particular community of interest or line of business.  This term may also refer to the governance group for a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<p>A NIEM <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> is sometimes associated with or managed by an organization independent of NIEM, and may have its own rules, procedures, schedule, and priorities.  The data components that make up NIEM are published as a set of <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef>.  Each <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> is composed of a set of schema documents that include a <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> schema document, special infrastructure schema documents (<code>structures.xsd</code> and <code>appinfo.xsd</code>), multiple <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> schema documents, and code table schema documents.  Each <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> or code table schema document has a body of <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> representatives that is responsible for its content and maintains its own timeline for updates and publication.  For this document, the term <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> applies to both <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> and code table working groups.</p>

	<p>For more information on what is included in a <termRef>NIEM core</termRef>, what <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and code table schema documents are defined, and what they contain, see <link>http://release.niem.gov</link>.</p>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Objectives"><title>Objectives</title>

	<p>The NIEM High Level Version Architecture (HLVA) described by this document is meant to achieve the following objectives:</p>

	<ul>
		<li><p>Each <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may publish updates on its own timeline.  This publication is not delayed by waiting for NBAC review.</p></li>		
		<li><p><termRef term="domain update">Domain updates</termRef> are quickly available for use in Information Exchange Package Documentation (IEPD).  A <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may accommodate IEPDs for its <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> as well as cross-domain IEPDs.  Updates may be used by IEPDs without being delayed by an <termRef term="domain update">update</termRef>, <termRef term="core synchronization">synchronization</termRef>, or <termRef>harmonization</termRef> process.</p></li>
		<li><p><termRef term="domain update">Domain updates</termRef> are incorporated into the next <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p></li>		
		<li><p>IEPD developers are provided with a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>, which is an updated schema document set that is <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef>, for increased usability.</p></li>
		<li><p>IEPDs have the flexibility to use NIEM components as needed to satisfy their business requirements.  An IEPD may reference components from one or more <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef>, as well as other published content.</p></li>		
		<li><p>There is a specific, concrete path for <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> to provide input to the NBAC's update, <termRef>core synchronization</termRef>, and <termRef>harmonization</termRef> processes, for inclusion in a future <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p>There is a reliable schedule for</p>
			<ul>
				<li><p><termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> activities</p></li>
				<li><p>NIEM <termRef term="minor release">minor releases</termRef> produced by <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef></p></li>
				<li><p><termRef>core synchronization</termRef> activities</p></li>
				<li><p>NIEM <termRef term="major release">major releases</termRef> produced by <termRef>core synchronization</termRef>.</p></li>
			</ul>
		    <p>Providing schedules ensures that participants in the activities know when their input is due and timelines for required work.  It also ensures that release users can plan for release dates.</p>
		</li>

		<li><p>All changes are visible.  Each namespace Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is used for exactly one version of a schema document, so any change results in a new namespace URI.  In addition, change logs support descriptions of changes made to namespaces.</p></li>
	</ul>



<section id="Not-Objectives"><title>Not Objectives</title>

	<p>The following are not objectives of the NIEM High Level Version Architecture (HLVA):</p>

	<ul>
		<li><p>Reuse of a single schema document target namespace URI for multiple versions of a schema document.  The methods of the HLVA create new schema documents with new URIs for changed, modified, and otherwise updated components.</p></li>
		<li><p>Definition of backwards compatibility or forwards compatibility between XML Schema documents.  The concept of compatibility between schema definitions is difficult to maintain without sacrificing precise schema validation.  The HLVA selected methods that allow for easy migration between schema document versions, while maintaining precise schema validation based on specific schema definitions.</p></li>
		<li><p>Description of specific criteria for <termRef>harmonization</termRef> and best practices for design of the contents of schema documents.  These will be addressed in other NIEM documents.</p></li>
		<li><p>Description of candidate releases and prereleases.  The NIEM HLVA is concerned only with schema documents and supporting artifacts that are durable, and for which there must be long-term support.  The use of candidate releases and prereleases will be addressed by recommendations on <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> governance and release strategy, which may be the subject of other NIEM documents.  Additional methods and functionality within the <termRef>collaboration area</termRef> to support prereleases will be described by the final version of the architecture specification.</p></li>	
	</ul>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Overview"><title>Overview</title>

	<p>The HLVA provides a framework for changes to be performed, in a systematic way, on a set of artifacts.  These are outlined in subparts of this section.  The activities that lead to changes in the schema documents and other artifacts are driven by a desire to improve the model.  Improvements include correcting errors, meeting previously unforeseen requirements, and adapting to new needs and new uses of the model.  One concern is how we define improvement to the model.  A common term for improving systems is <termRef>harmonization</termRef>, a term which we adopt for this effort.</p> 

	<definition term="harmonization">
		<p><em>Harmonization</em> (of a schema document or set of schema documents) is the process of modifying a schema document set in an incremental fashion for the purpose of improving the quality of the schema document set with respect to some criteria. For example, a schema document set may be harmonized to reduce semantic overlap of its components.  A schema document set may also be harmonized to ensure uniformity of the vocabulary used in definitions of its components.</p> 
	</definition>

	<p><termRef term="harmonization">Harmonization</termRef> may be conducted within a single schema document, or may be conducted across multiple schema documents of a schema document set.</p>

	<p>The version architecture does not anticipate that NIEM will ever be completely harmonized (a theoretically perfect state for a schema document set, in which all components perfectly satisfy all criteria).  In practice, a fully harmonized state is never reached, and the goal of <termRef>harmonization</termRef> is incremental improvement, rather than perfection.</p>

	<p>This section outlines the basic structure of the architecture.  Many details are in later sections.</p>



<section id="Classes-of-Information"><title>Classes of Information</title>

	<p>There are several classes of information that are employed by the version architecture.  They are defined as follows:</p>

	<definition term="model package description">
	<p>As defined by <ref idref="NIEM-MPD"/>:</p>
	<blockquote>
		<p>A <termRef>model package description</termRef> is a ZIP file (See <ref idref="PKZIP"/>) that:</p>
        	<ul>
        		<li><p>includes a set of logically cohesive W3C XML Schema documents and other supporting files that represent one or more reusable or implementable XML information models, and</p></li>
			<li><p>has an MPD class of <code>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/model-package-description/3.0/#MPD</code>, and</p></li>
			<li><p>adheres to all the rules in <ref idref="NIEM-MPD"/> for the <termRef>model package description</termRef> conformance target.</p></li>
	        </ul>
		<p>This term may be abbreviated <q>MPD</q>.</p>
	</blockquote>
	</definition>

	<definition term="NIEM release">
		<p>An <termRef term="model package description">MPD</termRef> that is a set of schema documents published by the NIEM PMO.  Each schema document defines data components for use in information exchanges.  A release should:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><p>be easy to use.</p></li>
			<li><p>define each concept in a <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> way.</p></li>
			<li><p>be independent of other releases, although any given schema document may occur in multiple releases.</p></li>
			<li><p>be of high quality, and has been vetted by <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef>.</p></li>
		</ul>
	</definition>

	<p>A <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> can be any one of three types:</p>

	<definition term="major release">
		<p>A <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> in which the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> reference schema document has changed since the previous <termRef term="NIEM release">releases</termRef>.  The first integer of the version number indicates the <termRef>major release</termRef> series; for example, NIEM versions 1.0, 2.0, and 3.0 are different <termRef term="major release">major releases</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="minor release">
		<p>A <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> in which the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> has not changed from previous <termRef term="NIEM release">releases</termRef> in the series, but at least one or more domain reference schema documents have changed.  A second integer greater than zero in the version number indicates a <termRef>minor release</termRef> (for example, NIEM version 2.1).  Note also that major version 2.0 and minor version 2.1 are in the same series (i.e., series 2) and contain the same <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> schema document.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="micro release">
		<p>A <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> in which neither the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> nor the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> reference schema documents have changed from the previous <termRef term="major release">major</termRef> or <termRef>minor release</termRef>, but one or more new reference schema documents have been added (without impact to <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> or <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> schemas).  A third integer greater than zero in the version number indicates a <termRef>micro release</termRef> (for example, NIEM version 2.1.1; note that this release does not currently exist).</p>
	</definition>

	<p>As a general rule, a published <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> is never revoked or removed from the <termRef>release area</termRef>.  However, updates to a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> may be published.</p>

	<definition term="published update">
		<p>A <termRef>published update</termRef> is a schema document or set of schema documents that is issued by a <termRef>NIEM domain</termRef> or <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef> body.  An update may be new content or may be an update of content that was previously included in a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  A <termRef>published update</termRef> may define new versions of content from <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM release</termRef> or other published content.  The issuing body vets each update before publication, but the update is not subject to review by other NIEM bodies.  A <termRef>published update</termRef> must be conformant, but otherwise it has fewer constraints on quality than does a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<p>There are currently two kinds of <termRef term="published update">published updates</termRef> in NIEM:</p>

	<definition term="domain update">
		<p>An <termRef term="model package description">MPD</termRef> that adds or modifies components in its own schema documents associated with a previously published <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  A <termRef>domain update</termRef> is published to the <termRef>publication area</termRef> by the <termRef>NIEM domain</termRef> owning the schema document that the <termRef>domain update</termRef> modifies.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="core supplement">
		<p>A special <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> <termRef term="model package description">MPD</termRef> that adds or supplements components in an existing (i.e., previously published) <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> within a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  A <termRef>core supplement</termRef> is published to the <termRef>publication area</termRef> by the NIEM PMO (at the recommendation of NBAC and NTAC).  A <termRef>core supplement</termRef> is additive or supplemental in nature; it cannot replace or modify components in a published <termRef>NIEM core</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<p>Through review and usage of published releases, potentially new or missing requirements, flaws, or other concerns will be identified in NIEM.  These <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> are recorded for review, discussion, and action (as needed) by <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef>.</p>  

	<definition term="NIEM issue">
		<p>Users of NIEM schema documents and components will find problems that should be addressed.  These will include erroneous syntax or definitions, inconsistencies between different parts of the model, and new requirements that are not yet satisfied.  A <termRef>NIEM issue</termRef> is a record of one of these problems.  An <termRef term="NIEM issue">issue<char name="rsquo"/>s</termRef> record may include discussion of the problem, possible solutions, and changes to the model required to resolve the problem.</p>
	</definition>

</section>


<section id="Data-Stores"><title>Data Stores</title>

	<p>There are several data stores in the architecture.  General terms are used here, to avoid introducing any requirements or restrictions associated with an existing tool, such as a registry, repository, or specific Web software such as Bugzilla or Sharepoint.  This description seeks only to describe requirements and functionality for these data stores.</p>

	<definition term="release area">
		<p>A network location at which <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> are stored and made publicly available.  The <termRef>release area</termRef> is <link>http://release.niem.gov/</link>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="publication area">
		<p>An Internet location that stores <termRef term="core supplement">core supplements</termRef>, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef>, code list updates, and other artifacts not produced during a NIEM release cycle, but are available for download and use with IEPDs.  The NIEM <termRef>publication area</termRef> is <link>http://publication.niem.gov/niem/</link>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="issue tracking area">
		<p>A tool or network location that supports registration, modification, and collaborative discussion of <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> pertaining to NIEM schema documents, concepts, data components, and other artifacts.  (This may be or may include the NCCT - NIEM Configuration and Control Tool.)</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="collaboration area">
		<p>A tool or network location that supports cooperative editing of artifacts, as well as discussion by <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and other NIEM working groups.  Each <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> or working group receives its own partition within the <termRef>collaboration area</termRef>.  Partitions are private; access to each is restricted to members of the appropriate working group.</p>
	</definition>

</section>



<section id="Activities"><title>Activities</title>

	<p>There are five major activities involved in managing versions of NIEM.  <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> representatives, NBAC, and NTAC engage in these processes as they improve and extend NIEM.</p>

	<definition term="domain update process">
		<p>A governance change process that results in a <termRef>domain update</termRef>.  A <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may publish updates to its schema documents to the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  A <termRef>domain update</termRef> proposes updates to future <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM release</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="core supplement process">
		<p>A governance process that results in a <termRef>core supplement</termRef>.  NBAC may publish supplements to a <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> to the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  A <termRef>core supplement</termRef> is always additive or supplemental in nature; it CANNOT replace or modify a <termRef>NIEM core</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="domain reconciliation">
		<p>A governance process through which NBAC resolves conflicts between <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef>.  This process results in a reconciled, <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> schema document set that is published as a <termRef>minor release</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="cross-domain harmonization">
		<p>A process through which NBAC initiates tiger teams and working groups to resolve inconsistencies, overlaps, and other semantic <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> between the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>, and between the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef>.  The results of these efforts will go into the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>, to be included in the next appropriate <termRef term="major release">major</termRef> or <termRef>minor release</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="core synchronization">
		<p>The results of <termRef>cross-domain harmonization</termRef> are merged into a new release of the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace, with <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> synchronized to the new <termRef>NIEM core</termRef>.  Together, these form a <termRef>major release</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

</section>



<section id="Walkthrough-Versioning"><title>A Walkthrough of Versioning</title>

	<p>The NIEM versioning process contains several activities, performed by various parties.  This section walks through these activities, and highlights the inputs and outputs of each.  Each activity and artifact is discussed in more detail in later sections.</p>

	<figure id="activities"><title>Activity flow for the NIEM versioning processes.</title>
		<image src="img/activities.png"/>
	</figure>

	<p>The following is a brief high-level walkthrough of versioning, and describes the processes diagrammed in <ref idref="activities"/>.  The items numbers are keyed to the diagram.</p>

	<ol>
		<li><p><termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> and <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef> are available for use in IEPDs and other use.</p></li>
		<li><p>Through use and analysis of <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> and published content, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> users will identify problems and new requirements for <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content.  Users include developers of IEPDs, as well as implementers and users of exchanges.</p></li>
		<li><p>These problems and requirements will be entered and tracked as <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> in the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p>NIEM <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> use <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> as the basis for incremental improvements, extensions, and proposed changes to <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef>.  This process is called the <termRef>domain update process</termRef>.  Domains may work together via a partition of the <termRef>collaboration area</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p><termRef term="NIEM domain">Domains</termRef> publish their <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef> in three ways:</p>
			<ul>
				<li><p><termRef term="NIEM issue">Issues</termRef> are updated and new <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> are entered into the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>.</p></li>
				<li><p><termRef term="NIEM domain">Domain</termRef> schema documents are updated in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.</p></li>
				<li><p>Optionally, a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may request to release <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> schema document changes via a NIEM <termRef>micro release</termRef> that is published in the <termRef>release area</termRef>.  A <termRef>micro release</termRef> is often <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> specific, and has a three-part numeric version identifier, such as 3.10.2.</p></li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		<li><p>Periodically, the NBAC reconciles <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef> into a new <termRef>minor release</termRef>.  The goals of this process are:</p>
			<ul>
				<li><p>to resolve the conflicts and inconsistencies that are created by new and modified <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> content</p></li>
				<li><p>to produce a <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> set of reference schema documents for the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef></p></li>
				<li><p>to perform some incremental <termRef>harmonization</termRef> on that schema document set.  This process is called <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef>, and is scheduled annually.  In this process, the NBAC examines <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef>, <termRef term="published update">published updates</termRef>, and releases, and reconciles changes to <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> into a single <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> schema document set.  The NBAC ensures that all <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> reference each other in a consistent way.</p></li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		<li><p>The result of this <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef> process is published as the next <termRef>minor release</termRef>.  This release is <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef>.  This release has a version identifier.  This release is called a NIEM <termRef>minor release</termRef>, and it contains no modification to the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace.  It may contain some additional <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content (in a new namespace), but will not modify the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace.  This is published annually, as the result of <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef>.  A <termRef>minor release</termRef> has a two-part numeric version identifier that does not end in <q>0</q>, such as <q>4.2</q>.  For those <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> that are not resolved via <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef>, <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> in the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef> are updated, created, and closed, as appropriate.</p></li>
		<li><p>At any time, asynchronously with other processes, NBAC or NTAC may initiate a tiger team to conduct <termRef>cross-domain harmonization</termRef>.  A tiger team is a small working group of subject matter experts (SMEs) formed to solve a specific set of problems.  A tiger team exists only for a short time; it is disbanded once it has served its purpose.</p></li>
		<li><p>A tiger team that is formed by the NBAC or NTAC will solve some set of problems with the NIEM model.  For example, it may resolve a set of major <termRef>harmonization</termRef> <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> between the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef>.  Or, it may address a new requirement that requires thought and experience.  Or, it may identify, within the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>, components with semantic overlap, and will pull them up into <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> for common definition and use.  This process is called <termRef>cross-domain harmonization</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p>The results of tiger teams will be made available in a partition of the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  This partition may hold schema documents that contain additions to and extensions of the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace.  Each schema document is published with a unique namespace, distinct from the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace.  The <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> may use these schema documents in <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef>, and IEPDs may use these schema documents, as well.  The contents of these partitions of the <termRef>publication area</termRef> will be considered during the <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> process (step 6, above), and a supporting schema document containing additional <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content may be published with the periodic <termRef>minor release</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Every third year, the results of <termRef>cross-domain harmonization</termRef> and <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> are brought together into a new NIEM <termRef>major release</termRef> (instead of a <termRef>minor release</termRef>).  This process is called <termRef>core synchronization</termRef>.  The <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace is updated with help from resolved <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> in the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>, as well as the published <termRef term="domain update">updates</termRef> from the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and tiger teams.  Domain definitions that were dependent on the previous <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> are harmonized with the updated <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace.</p></li>
		<li><p><termRef term="core synchronization">Core synchronization</termRef> results in a new NIEM <termRef>major release</termRef>, with an updated <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace.  A <termRef>major release</termRef> has a two-part numeric version identifier that ends in <q>0</q>, such as <q>4.0</q>.</p></li>
	</ol>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Activities2"><title>Activities</title>

	<p>This section contains further discussion and details of the major activities of the NIEM version architecture.</p>



<section id="Domain-Reconciliation"><title>Domain Reconciliation</title>

	<p>Once a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> is published, updates and requests for changes accumulate.  Users post <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> (in the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>) describing problems with and unmet requirements of NIEM schema documents.</p>

	<p>In response to these <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef>, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> publish <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef> to their namespaces.  They identify and define new content that they require.  They define and update code tables that they require.  These updates are published in the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> partitions of the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.</p>

	<p>The NIEM Business Architecture Committee (NBAC) reconciles these requests with the latest published release, in order to produce a <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> NIEM schema document set.  This reconciliation will result in a schema document set that is easily used by IEPD developers.</p>

	<p>The NBAC makes decisions on how to accommodate changes.  In the <termRef>publication area</termRef>, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> publish updates prior to NBAC approval, ensuring autonomy of the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>.  The NBAC determines how best to migrate these updates into the next <termRef>minor release</termRef>.  The NBAC conducts <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> annually.</p>

	<p>This <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef> process will consist of the following stages:</p>

	<ol>
		<li><p>Gather and prepare input to the <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef> process.</p>
			<p>This input will come from open <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> in the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>, and from <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> partitions of the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  The content of the <termRef>publication area</termRef> will be evaluated for impacts.  Reports will be prepared that may include:</p>

		<ul>
			<li><p>Reports describing the impacts of proposed changes on other <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> namespaces.</p></li>
			<li><p>Reports assembling the comments that other <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> have made about proposed changes.</p></li>
			<li><p>Reports containing technical metrics that quantify the</p>
					<ul>
						<li><p>consistency of <termRef>harmonization</termRef> on the input schema document set, and</p></li> 
						<li><p>impacts of proposed changes.</p></li>
					</ul>
			</li>
			<li><p>NTAC recommendations on technical methods and techniques for handling <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> requests.</p></li>
			<li><p>Conformance <ref idref="NIEM-NDR"/> and quality checks <ref idref="NIEM-QASP"/>.  Conformance and quality checks are performed prior to publication of schema documents to the <termRef>publication area</termRef>, but additional reports on quality and conformance may be made available to the NBAC for <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef>.</p></li>
		</ul></li>

		<li><p>Reconcile proposed <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef>.</p></li>
	</ol>

	<p>Starting with the previous <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>, the NBAC will review and apply the changes that were requested by the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>.  For each proposed <termRef>domain update</termRef>, approve the update, or modify it as required to maintain high quality across all NIEM schema documents.</p>

	<p>When a change is applied, make modifications in other <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>, as required, to keep the schema document set <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef>.  Where <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef> introduce integrity issues, modify the schema document set to eliminate those problems.  Propagate <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef> through impacted namespaces, as appropriate.</p>

	<p>Note that there is no requirement or implication that any <termRef>harmonization</termRef> will be done by tools, or automatically in any way.  The goal of this architecture is to ensure that the responsible party has the authority, schedule, goal, and ability to do what is needed to ensure that <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> changes result in a <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> set of <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> schema documents that can easily be used in IEPDs.</p>



<section id="NBAC-Decisions"><title>NBAC Decisions</title>

	<p>Through the process of <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef>, the NBAC will resolve many <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> of cross-domain conflict.  This may include changes to one <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> that affect another <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef>, or overlaps of content between <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>.  Through the reconciliation process, the NBAC will make adjustments as-needed to ensure that <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef> do not harm the quality of the <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> as a whole.</p>

	<p>During its periodic <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef>, the NBAC may conduct additional <termRef>harmonization</termRef>.  Issues addressed may be <q>low hanging fruit</q>, such as particularly easy or notable problems.  Or, the NBAC may try to resolve one or more aspects of <termRef>harmonization</termRef> across the NIEM model, such as vocabulary consistency.  During <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef>, it is likely that time will be short, and the level of effort will be limited.  So, during reconciliation, extremely broad changes would be avoided, as would changes that required significant consideration by subject matter experts.  Such <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> would be handled by tiger teams and small groups in a separate process referred to as <termRef>cross-domain harmonization</termRef>.</p>

	<p>The NBAC, as the designated body for <termRef>harmonization</termRef>, may make any decision that it deems prudent to integrate <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef> with the previous <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  This may include the modification of dependent namespaces to accommodate <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> changes, the creation of new elements for indirect (substitution) methods, and the modification of definitions and component names.</p>

	<p>The NBAC may also choose to reject, in whole or in part, any <termRef>domain update</termRef>.  The rejected domain content is still available (without change) in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  However, it will not be part of <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef>, and will not be included in future <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef>.  The NBAC has the responsibility to act in the best interest of the entire NIEM community; it rejects domain content only to protect community interests, and it provides written justification when doing so.</p>

</section>



<section id="Coherence"><title>Coherence</title>

	<p>This document uses the term <termRef>coherence</termRef> to describe whether components of a schema document set refer to each other in a consistent manner:</p>

	<definition term="coherence">
		<p>A schema document set is <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> when it has the following properties:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><p>It does not refer to a schema document outside the set, and</p></li>
			<li><p>It does not include two different versions of the same component in an incompatible way.</p></li>
		</ul>
	</definition>

	<p>The coherence of a NIEM schema document set is best described by comparing a set that is not coherent with one that is.  Imagine the following sequence of events, leading to the situation in <ref idref="incoherent"/>:</p>

	<ul>
		<li><p>Domain B publishes version 1 of its content, including a <code>ThingID</code> component.</p></li>
		<li><p>Domain A reuses that <code>ThingID</code> component within a Domain A component.</p></li>
		<li><p>Domain B publishes version 2 of its content, which contains a modified <code>ThingID</code> component.</p></li>
		<li><p>An IEPD developer wishes to reuse components from the latest versions of Domain A and Domain B.  This results in the schema document set shown in <ref idref="incoherent"/>.</p></li>
	</ul>
	
	<figure id="incoherent"><title>A schema document set that is not <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef></title>
		<image src="img/non-coherent.png"/>
	</figure>

	<p>The schema document set in <ref idref="incoherent"/> is not coherent, because it contains two versions of the same element:  the new <code>ThingID</code> element in <code>domainB-2</code>, and the old <code>ThingID</code> element used in <code>domainA-1</code>.  This is a duplication of semantics.</p>

	<p>An IEPD with schema document sets that are not <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> can require significant work to make its schema documents work together.  For example, the IEPD author might design an extension namespace to duplicate the changes to <code>domainB-1:ThingID</code> that distinguishes it from <code>domainB-2:ThingID</code>.  These changes would likely cascade to related XML types, and similar changes would be required for each incompatibility between versions.  Such an environment, in which many <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> are updating frequently, will ultimately present IEPD developers with substantial problems.</p>

	<p>This problem will be resolved when Domain A publishes version 2 of its content, taking care to reuse components from version 2 of Domain B.  Afterwards, the IEPD developer using the latest versions of Domains A and B will be working with the coherent schema document set shown in <ref idref="coherent"/>.</p>

	<figure id="coherent"><title>A <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> schema document set</title>
		<image src="img/coherent.png"/>
	</figure>

	<p>Such a schema document set would not require custom extensions to fix problems related to <termRef term="coherence">incoherence</termRef>.  A later version of the version architecture specification will address specific rules for and the structure of version identifiers in the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> schema documents.  For example, it may be desirable for version identifiers for <q>bumped</q> namespaces to be easily distinguished from version identifiers for domain-initiated changes.</p>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Micro-Releases"><title>NIEM Micro Releases</title>

	<p>When a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> has created its updated content, it may determine that the content should be released as a <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef> <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  This will be verified by tools that check conformance and <termRef>coherence</termRef> of the resulting schema document set.  Once these checks are complete, a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may wish to publish its update directly as a NIEM <termRef>micro release</termRef> in the <termRef>release area</termRef>, rather than as a <termRef>published update</termRef> in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  To do so, the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> must request and receive NBAC approval.</p>

	<p>Schemas published in this manner may be more durable than schema documents published to the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  That is, schema documents so published may work better with more versions of NIEM.  <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> will not refer to schema documents in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>; schema documents from the <termRef>publication area</termRef> are reconciled and modified before their release, and they receive new target namespace URIs.  Schemas published directly to releases avoid reconciliation.  They also will not have to be modified as they go from the <termRef>publication area</termRef> to the <termRef>release area</termRef>, as they avoid the first step.  A prime candidate, and simple example, of this method is a code table.  By defining a code element such that it is substitutable for an element from a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>, multiple versions of a schema document set may be usable at the same time.  A new version of such a code table may be released as part of a NIEM <termRef>micro release</termRef> without requiring rework of other schema documents.  NIEM <termRef term="micro release">micro releases</termRef> require tools for validation and verification.  They also require a commitment to frequent <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef>, with limited vetting.</p>

</section>



<section id="Cross-Domain-Harmonization"><title>Cross-Domain Harmonization</title>

	<p>Larger and deeper <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> of semantic consistency and modeling will be addressed by tiger teams and small groups of subject matter experts, as determined by the NBAC.  The tasks to be undertaken by these <termRef>cross-domain harmonization</termRef> teams typically do not require participation from the entire NBAC.  The use of such teams will enable parallel <termRef>harmonization</termRef> efforts.  This will result in greater scalability, as the number of <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> increase.</p>

	<p>The products of <termRef>cross-domain harmonization</termRef> will include:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><p>Recommendations for <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef> in future <termRef term="minor release">minor releases</termRef>, and</p></li>
		<li><p>Additional <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> content provided via extensions and augmentations in new schema documents within the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.</p></li>
	</ul>

	<p>The additions to <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> that appear within the <termRef>publication area</termRef> may be immediately used by IEPDs, and <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> may base <termRef term="published update">published updates</termRef> on those schema documents.</p>

</section>



<section id="Core-Synchronization"><title>Core Synchronization</title>

	<p>Periodically, these products will be synchronized with <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content, to produce a new <termRef>major release</termRef>.  A <termRef>major release</termRef> will contain a new <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace.  A <termRef>major release</termRef> is the opportunity to change the existing <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content by removing or altering core components.  At the time of a <termRef>major release</termRef>, other major changes to the <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> schema document set may be considered by the NBAC, such as changes to <code>structures</code> and <code>appinfo</code>, which are schema documents that are part of the NIEM infrastructure.  For more information on <code>structures</code> and <code>appinfo</code>, see the <ref idref="NIEM-NDR"/> and other documents on the NIEM Web site at <link>http://reference.niem.gov/</link>.</p>

	<p>NIEM <termRef>core synchronization</termRef> will occur every third year.  However, a NIEM <termRef>core synchronization</termRef> may be held back for a longer period if changes to be released do not meet certain thresholds in terms of volume or severity.  The NBAC must balance the need for regular scheduled releases with the set of components that must be harmonized across <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> for inclusion into the <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef>.</p>

	<p>In between updates to <termRef>NIEM core</termRef>, the NBAC may add <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content via additional components in additional schema documents in a <termRef>minor release</termRef> of NIEM, without updating the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> schema document.  These would be additive changes only, and would not modify the original <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> schema document in any way.</p>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Releases"><title>NIEM Releases</title>

	<p>The NBAC <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> activity results in a NIEM <termRef>minor release</termRef>.</p>



<section id="Properties-of-Release">	<title>Properties of a NIEM Release</title>

	<p>A <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> has the following properties:</p>

	<ul>
		<li><p>The release is <termRef term="coherence">coherent</termRef>; that is, it contains only a single version of each <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> namespace.</p></li>
		<li><p>The release integrates the latest input from the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>, with accommodations made by the NBAC to make them work together.</p></li>
		<li><p>The release contains new versions of only those namespaces that require update.  Schema documents that require no update will be part of the release without modification.</p></li>
		<li><p>If required, a namespace will be updated to accommodate changes in other namespaces.  This is determined by the NBAC during the reconciliation process.</p></li>

	</ul>
</section>



<section id="Status-of-Release"><title>Status of a NIEM Release</title>

	<p>There are two types of <termRef>harmonization</termRef>/reconciliation:</p>

	<ol>
		<li><p>between the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> (<termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef>), and</p></li>
		<li><p>with <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> and the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> (<termRef>core synchronization</termRef>)</p></li>
	</ol>
	
	<p>This provides an opportunity to distinguish between the subsequent releases.  Reconciliation of <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> results in a <termRef>minor release</termRef>, while reconciliation of <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> results in a <termRef>major release</termRef>.</p>

</section>



<section id="Version-Identifiers-for-Releases"><title>Version Identifiers for NIEM Releases</title>

	<p>Domain-synchronized <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> are given <termRef>minor release</termRef> version numbers.  NIEM core-synchronized <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> are given <termRef>major release</termRef> version numbers.  Direct releases due to <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef> are given <termRef>micro release</termRef> numbers.</p>

	<p>When <termRef>core synchronization</termRef> occurs, the results are published as a NIEM <termRef>major release</termRef>.  These releases will be given identifiers such as 2.0, 3.0, and 4.0.  These releases will yield a <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace that has the same version identifier as the <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p>

	<p>When <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> occurs, without update of the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace, the results are published as a NIEM <termRef>minor release</termRef>.  These releases have identifiers such as 2.1, 2.2, 2.3, 3.1, 3.2, and 3.3.  When a <termRef>domain update process</termRef> occurs without reconciliation, the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may request from NBAC a new release that incorporates that update, and the results are published as a NIEM <termRef>micro release</termRef>.  These releases have identifiers such as 2.1.1, 2.1.2, 2.2.1, and 2.2.2.</p>

	<p>For <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> identifiers, <termRef term="major release">major releases</termRef> have two integers (e.g., 2.0).  The major integer (2), and the minor integer (.0).  The <termRef>minor release</termRef> following 2.0 is 2.1.  The <termRef>micro release</termRef> following 2.1 is 2.1.1.  There is no version 2.1.0.</p>

	<p>For <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> identifiers, the value following 2.9 is 2.10.  Each number (major, minor, or micro) is a field storing an integer, not a single digit.</p>

	<p>The version identifiers for released <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> schema documents (in the <termRef>release area</termRef>) and published schema documents (in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>) are not described by this HLVA.  Constraints on these identifiers have not yet been determined, and will be specified fully in future version of the version architecture specification.</p>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Data-Stores2"><title>Data Stores</title>

	<p>The version architecture defines several areas in which artifacts of NIEM are stored.  Each may be implemented using new or existing tools.  The goal of this document is to describe the areas, what information they contain, and what functionality is needed to support activities that use these areas.</p>

	<p>The specific software and tools that make up these data stores are not specified by this document.  Such specifications will be detailed by later documents.</p>



<section id="Release-Area"><title>The Release Area</title>

	<p>All releases of NIEM are published to the <termRef>release area</termRef>.</p>

	<p>All schema documents published to the <termRef>release area</termRef> are persistent, and are available for immediate use by IEPD developers and other users.</p>

	<p>A single schema document may be a part of multiple releases.  For example, a single release of the <termRef>NIEM core</termRef> namespace will be a part of one or more <termRef term="minor release">minor releases</termRef>.  The <termRef>release area</termRef> will provide metadata to make clear exactly which schema documents are associated with which releases.  This metadata is referred to as the <termRef>release manifest</termRef>.  The format of this metadata is yet to be determined.  The <termRef>release area</termRef> is <link>http://release.niem.gov/</link>.</p>

</section>



<section id="Collaboration-Area"><title>The Collaboration Area</title>

	<p>The <termRef>collaboration area</termRef> supports cooperative editing of artifacts, as well as discussion by <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and other NIEM working groups.  Each <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> or working group receives its own partition within the <termRef>collaboration area</termRef>.</p>

	<p>These partitions are private, as access to each partition is restricted to the members of the appropriate working group.</p>

	<p>The precise mechanics and content of the <termRef>collaboration area</termRef> are to be determined.</p>

</section>



<section id="Publication-Area"><title>The Publication Area</title>

	<p>The <termRef>publication area</termRef> is a well-known location for <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and other working groups to publish schema documents and other artifacts for NIEM.  This has two major purposes:</p>

	<ol>
		<li><p>It allows published content to be immediately used.</p></li>
		<li><p>It provides a concrete method for changes to be expressed for <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> and <termRef>core synchronization</termRef>.</p></li>
	</ol>
	
	<p>All content of the <termRef>publication area</termRef> is persistent.  That is, it never goes away once it is published.  Also, it is never modified.  Revised versions of published content may also be published, however, no artifact is removed or revised.  This ensures that all content of the <termRef>publication area</termRef> may be freely used by any development effort, without fear of it changing or disappearing.  All content of the <termRef>publication area</termRef> is available for use by IEPD developers, as well as developers of other schema documents and applications.</p> 



<section id="Parititions-of-PA"><title>Partitions of the Publication Area</title>

	<p>Each <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> and working group controls a partition of the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.  This partition is the publication site for products of the working group.  The <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may place any number of schema documents into its <termRef>publication area</termRef>.</p>

</section>



<section id="Use-of-PA"><title>Use of the Publication Area</title>

	<p>Schema documents within the <termRef>publication area</termRef> may provide additional content, or describe other changes to a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  Here is how the <termRef>publication area</termRef> is used:</p>

	<ul>
		<li><p>After a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef> is published, it becomes available for use by IEPDs.  Through use and analysis of that <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> users will identify problems and new requirements for <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> content and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content.  These will be conveyed via the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p>The <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef>, under its own governance, determines what changes it believes should be made to the latest NIEM distribution.  It expresses these changes by publishing schema documents and supporting metadata in its <termRef>publication area</termRef> partition.  Requests by the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> for changes to other <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> will be made through the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef> and the NCCT.</p></li>
		<li><p>Schema documents published to the <termRef>publication area</termRef> are immediately available for use by IEPDs.  Both <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> IEPDs and cross-domain IEPDs may use any schema documents in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>, as they require.</p></li>
		<li><p>The schema documents, supporting metadata, and <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> (in the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>) describe changes the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> makes to its <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> and requests for changes to <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content.  The requested changes are considered by the NBAC, and are reconciled with the last release, and with changes requested by other <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p>The result of the NBAC reconciliation is published as the next <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p></li>
	</ul>
	
	<p>Schemas in the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> partition of the <termRef>publication area</termRef> may extend components within a <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM release</termRef>, instead of superseding namespaces within <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM release</termRef>.</p>

	<p>The schema documents in NIEM 2.0 contained schema documents that superseded the schema documents in NIEM 1.0.  Schema documents in the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> <termRef term="publication area">publication areas</termRef> are not required to supersede older schema documents in this manner.  Instead, schema documents in the <termRef>publication area</termRef> may extend schema documents in previous NIEM distributions.  This may make <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain updates</termRef> easier to use by IEPDs.  For example, suppose <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> <code>JXDM</code> wishes to add an element <code>ArrestSubject</code> to the type <code>ArrestType</code> that occurred in JXDM-4.0.  It may publish a schema document in its <termRef>publication area</termRef> that extends the JXDM 4.0 <code>ArrestType</code>.  This extension may then add <code>ArrestSubject</code> to the <code>ArrestType</code>.  A substitutable element may be made to provide for the new <code>ArrestType</code> to be used in IEPDs.</p>

	<p>Extensions made in the manner above may be easier for IEPDs to use than replacement components.  When a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> publishes an update as an extension of the latest release, that update may be easier for an IEPD to use than if it was published as a replacement of the latest release.</p>

	<p>The specific method used in a <termRef>domain update</termRef> is left for the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> to determine.  Some <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> may choose to replace components, while others may extend components.  It is expected that best practices will be determined over time.  Best practices may vary from <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> to <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef>, as some <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> may prefer to use common extensions, while others may prefer that each IEPD do its own integration work.</p>

</section>



<section id="Namespaces-for-PA-Content"><title>Namespaces for Content of the Publication Area</title>

	<p>Each schema document that is posted to the <termRef>publication area</termRef> will have a namespace that meets several criteria.</p>

		<ul>
			<li><p>It is unique to the posted schema document.  There will not be two schema documents posted to the <termRef>publication area</termRef> that have the same namespace URI.</p></li>
			<li><p>It clearly identifies that it is a namespace from the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.</p></li>
			<li><p>It clearly identifies the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> or working group that is responsible for it.</p></li>
			<li><p>It clearly identifies a version of the schema document target namespace.  An example is <link>http://publication.niem.gov/niem/domains/cyfs/2.1/</link>, where the namespace is similar to that in a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>, but with <code>publication</code> instead of <code>release</code>.</p></li>
		</ul>

</section>



<section id="Additional-Requirements-of-PA"><title>Additional Requirements of the Publication Area</title>

	<p>Each schema document in the <termRef>publication area</termRef> has a target namespace that is distinct from that of all other schema documents.  There will not be two different schema documents in the <termRef>publication area</termRef> with the same namespace, nor will there be a schema document in the <termRef>publication area</termRef> with the same namespace as a schema document in a <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p>

	<p>Each schema document in the <termRef>publication area</termRef> is persistent.  Like the schema documents in <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef>, once published, the schema documents will not go away.  These schema documents will remain available for use by IEPDs.</p>

	<p>Schema documents in the <termRef>publication area</termRef> will be accompanied by <termRef term="change log">change logs</termRef>, which give comprehensible descriptions of the changes that were made to schema documents.  This is discussed in <ref idref="Change-Log"/>.</p>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Issue-Tracking-Area"><title>The Issue Tracking Area</title>

	<p>NIEM currently conducts <termRef>NIEM issue</termRef> tracking using the NIEM Configuration Control Tool (NCCT).  This is an <termRef term="NIEM issue">issue</termRef> tracking system with forums for the NTAC, NBAC, and <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>.  This document uses the more general terminology <q><termRef>issue tracking area</termRef></q> rather than referring directly to the NCCT, as whether the version architecture will use the NCCT in its current form is yet to be determined.</p>

	<p>The purpose of the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef> is to capture and track requirements and problems from end users, developers, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>, and other people and bodies associated with NIEM.  Although <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> come from users, whether or not users will directly interact with the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef> is yet to be determined.  Issues may be entered by a helpdesk, in order to ensure that duplicates are not entered, and that <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> are specified fully and clearly, so that additional work is not created downstream.</p>

	<p>The <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef> may include a conventional <termRef term="NIEM issue">issue</termRef> tracking system as well as forums/bulletin boards for discussing <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef>.  Each <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> and working group may be given a partition of the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>, as needed.  These groups will have control over their <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef>, and may dispatch them and resolve them as desired.</p>

	<p>To be determined is whether a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may also have <termRef term="NIEM issue">issue</termRef> tracking systems and methods outside the NIEM-provided <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef>.  This will reduce transparency, and may impair cooperation between working groups.  It may also increase error when moving <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> from one body to another.</p>

	<p>One group may delegate an <termRef term="NIEM issue">issue</termRef> to another group, when the alternate group is better able to address the <termRef term="NIEM issue">issue</termRef>.</p>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Additional-Artifacts"><title>Additional Artifacts</title>



	<section id="Release-Manifest"><title>Release Manifest</title>


	<definition term="release manifest">
		<p>An artifact that lists many schema documents, each of which may be a part of multiple releases.  A <termRef>release manifest</termRef> expresses</p> 
		<ul>
			<li><p>what are the <termRef term="NIEM release">releases</termRef> in the <termRef>release area</termRef>, and</p></li>
			<li><p>what schema documents are parts of each <termRef term="NIEM release">release</termRef>.</p></li>
		</ul>
	</definition>

	<p>The mechanics and format of the <termRef>release manifest</termRef> are to be determined.  There may be a single <termRef term="release manifest">manifest</termRef> for all contents of the <termRef>release area</termRef>.  There may also be an individual <termRef term="release manifest">manifest</termRef> for each <termRef term="NIEM release">release</termRef>.</p>

	</section>



	<section id="Change-Log"><title>Change Log</title>

	<definition term="change log">
		<p>An artifact that describes the changes applied to an <termRef term="model package description">MPD</termRef> since its previous version.</p>
	</definition>

		<p>The <termRef>publication area</termRef> will contain <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef>.  These updates are provided as XML Schema documents, and will be accompanied by a <termRef>change log</termRef>.</p>

		<p>A <termRef>change log</termRef> is able to express a single big change that is composed of a set of small changes.  For example, the renaming of an element may include changes to many types that used that element.</p>

		<p>Without a <termRef>change log</termRef>, changes made between versions of a schema document would not include an expression of what the changes to the schema document might mean.  Although the revised schema document may be fully formed and well defined, it may be unclear what impact the change might have on other schema documents.</p>

		<p>For example, upon renaming an element (from an old name to a new name), the change is represented in XML Schema by the original element (with the old name) not appearing in the revised schema document, and a new element (with the new name) appearing in the revised schema document.</p>

		<p>A type in another <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may be impacted by this change.  If the type used the original element with the old name, it would be unclear what changes should be made to the type to accommodate the renaming.</p>

		<p>In order to describe changes to schema documents with enough detail to enable <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef>, schema document definitions are accompanied by metadata that describe changes.  This metadata will include a list of changes, without restating the details that occur in the schema documents that are in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.</p>

		<p>The mechanics and format of the <termRef>change log</termRef> are to be determined.  The format will be in XML, and may include XPath expressions for relating <termRef>change log</termRef> entries to updated schema documents.  The <termRef>change log</termRef> XML file may describe the following about each change made by a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef>:</p>

		<ul>
			<li><p>A description of the change, which says what was done and, perhaps, why it was done.</p></li>
			<li><p>A list of the components that were added as a result of the change.  It may include the location of each new component, via XPath locations.  It may also describe the location (in the sequence of the original component) where an element may be inserted into a type.</p></li>
			<li><p>A list of the components that were deleted as a result of the change.  (Note that no change actually deletes anything as all schema documents are persistent, but deleted components will not exist in future schema documents)</p></li>
			<li><p>A list of modifications, each modification giving the location of the original definition and the location of the new definition.</p></li>
		</ul>

		<p>Users will be able to audit <termRef term="change log">change logs</termRef> against schema document updates to look for</p>
			<ul>
				<li><p>changes and updates that are inadequately described by the <termRef>change log</termRef>, and</p></li>
				<li><p>changes in the <termRef>change log</termRef> that is not correlated by updated content.  Such a change log may be audited when uploaded, before publication of the schema documents and <termRef>change log</termRef> to the <termRef>publication area</termRef>.</p></li>
			</ul>

			<p>Descriptions of the changes made are provided to the NBAC during <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef>, and would help them to determine the contents of the next <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p>

	</section>



	<section id="Namespace-URI-Directive"><title>Namespace URI Directive</title>

		<p>Through the NBAC's <termRef>domain reconciliation</termRef> process, it may be determined that some namespaces must be adjusted to accommodate changes to other namespaces.  That is, although the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> has no new updates for its namespace, the NBAC must change the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> namespace to accommodate changes in other <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>.  In this situation, we say that the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> namespace was <termRef term="bump">bumped</termRef>.</p>

		<definition term="bump">
			<p>A process whereby a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> schema document requires a new target namespace URI as a result of one or more changes made to another <termRef term="NIEM domain">NIEM domain</termRef> schema document that impact the content of the schema document to be <termRef term="bump">bumped</termRef>.</p>
		</definition>

		<p>The version architecture does not allow the application of changes directly to a published namespace.  A changed schema document must be given a new target namespace URI.  So, when a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> namespace is <termRef term="bump">bumped</termRef>, it must be given a new namespace URI.</p>

		<definition term="namespace URI directive">
			<p>An artifact that specifies the new target namespace URI for a new schema document resulting from the need to <termRef>bump</termRef> it.</p>
		</definition>

		<p>The exact mechanics of how a <termRef>namespace URI directive</termRef> is published is to be determined.  One option is for it to be an XML file that is published in the <termRef>publication area</termRef>, within the domain's partition.</p>

		<p>There are several goals for the <termRef>namespace URI directive</termRef>:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><p>to provide clear direction to those building a <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM release</termRef> regarding how to construct namespaces for <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> schema documents</p></li>
			<li><p>to enable <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> to maintain control of their namespace URIs, and the progression of those URIs from version to version.  It is expected that a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> may wish to exert strong control over the version identifiers for its schema documents.</p></li>
		</ul>

		<p>The <termRef>namespace URI directive</termRef> allows the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> to express the structure of its target namespace URIs, and the sequence of version identifiers.  The <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> will be able to specify how namespace URIs are incremented when the namespace is updated or <termRef term="bump">bumped</termRef>.</p>

	</section>

</section>



<section id="Timelines"><title>General Release Timelines</title>

	<p>The NIEM version architecture is designed to be agile, accommodate regular change, and respond efficiently to stakeholder requirements.  To do so, NIEM maintains the ability to execute predictable, repeatable, and consistent <termRef term="release cycle">release cycles</termRef>, while also allowing its <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> to publish updates independently (on their own timelines).  At a high level, this section describes the timelines, coordination, and options for major and minor <termRef term="release cycle">release cycles</termRef>.</p>

	<definition term="release cycle">
		<p>A period of time during which appropriate groups of <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef> and <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> representatives engage in the activities that result in a major or minor <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<p>NIEM will generally publish an annual <termRef term="NIEM release">release</termRef> in the same quarter of each year.  The normal target is the third quarter of the Government fiscal year (subject to change as determined by NIEM goverance and the PMO).  Within each three-year period, the NIEM program will execute two consecutive minor <termRef term="release cycle">release cycles</termRef>, followed by a major <termRef>release cycle</termRef>.</p>
			
	<p>A release date will be scheduled (internally established by the PMO) for the beginning of the target quarter.  The release date may shift later in the quarter if necessary.  This adds a degree of flexibility and safety to the schedule to accommodate additional pre-release phases (e.g., Beta2 or beta3) or other unforeseen events, while still maintaining consistency and predictability.  NIEM PMO will communicate anticipated scheduling details to the NIEM Community for planning.</p>

	<p>If required to meet schedule, a <termRef>release cycle</termRef> may be time-boxed or content-scoped (or both).</p>
	
	<p>For each <termRef>release cycle</termRef>, the PMO will assign a release coordinator selected from the major stakeholders.  The release coordinator will monitor and report progress to PMO, NTAC, NBAC, and domains, resolve issues of schedule and scope, and coordinate participating entities (<termRef>NIEM governance</termRef>, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef>, release manager, etc.).</p>
	
	<p>Ordinarily NIEM will not issue a <termRef>minor release</termRef> for a previous major version series (such as version 2.0).  However, a request by a <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> (or other entity) to issue a <termRef>minor release</termRef> for such (e.g., a request for a Version 2.2) will be jointly considered by PMO, NBAC, and NTAC.  If approved, it will be executed between annual <termRef term="release cycle">release cycles</termRef> (since the scope of change is expected to be small).</p>



<section id="Release-Cycle-Stages"><title>Release Cycle Stages</title>

	<p>A typical NIEM <termRef>release cycle</termRef> is comprised of three basic stages of development, each of which may require several iterations.  These are defined as follows:</p>

	<definition term="alpha">
		<p>The initial stage of a <termRef>release cycle</termRef>.  Primary activities focus on integrating architectural improvements (if any) as well as <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> content changes previously prepared as <termRef term="domain update">domain</termRef> and <termRef term="core supplement">core supplements</termRef> since the last <termRef term="NIEM release">release</termRef>.  Other activities include <termRef term="domain reconciliation">reconciliation</termRef>, <termRef>core synchronization</termRef> (when appropriate), appropriate types of <termRef>harmonization</termRef>, refactoring/refinement of content as needed, application of resolved <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef>, and iterative <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef> reviews and feedback.  The most significant types, volume, and scale of changes occur during <termRef>alpha</termRef> stage.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="beta">
		<p>The midterm stage of a <termRef>release cycle</termRef>.  At the beginning of this stage the developing release has stabilized to the degree that remaining changes are minor <char name="mdash"/> major adjustments for architecture have been completed; no significant new content may be integrated; release schemas are in a state that will allow user beta testing (i.e., the release is expected to be NIEM-conformant).  Changes are still allowed; however, these are much smaller in magnitude and complexity and are generally only corrections and adjustments.  Examples of <termRef>beta</termRef> stage changes include adjustments to data component structure; movement of properties; renaming and redefining; addition or refinement of keyword, usage, and example metadata (associated with definitions); addition of a very small number new components (essentially inadvertent omissions or additions needed to adjust structure), and occasionally very minor corrections to architecture.  If <termRef>beta</termRef> testing, reviews, and feedback discover major flaws that require significant changes, then the release may revert back to the <termRef>alpha</termRef> stage.</p>
	</definition>

	<definition term="release candidate">
		<p>The final stage of a <termRef>release cycle</termRef>.  A <termRef>release candidate</termRef> should be identical to, and therefore is a potential final production (i.e., operational) <termRef term="NIEM release">release</termRef>.  Only extremely minor corrections to a <termRef>release candidate</termRef> are allowed.  These include minor corrections to character strings, names, definitions, namespaces, etc.  At this stage absolutely NO architectural or significant content changes are allowed.  Any such changes will require regenerating the release as a <termRef>beta</termRef> product.  Activities during this stage are essentially only testing, review, feedback, and possibly very minor refinements.  As this is the final review, diligence must ensure quality and conformance before publication.  If testing, reviews, and feedback discover flaws that require significant changes, then the release may revert back to the <termRef>beta</termRef>, or even <termRef>alpha</termRef> stage.  Very minor refinements to a <termRef>release candidate</termRef> will require regenerating it as a new <termRef>release candidate</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<p>In the past, NIEM has often referred to a so-called <termRef>pre-alpha</termRef> stage.  In fact, this is not a formal stage of a NIEM <termRef>release cycle</termRef>.</p>

	<definition term="pre-alpha">
		<p>Any time period during which the NIEM program is NOT executing a <termRef>release cycle</termRef>, i.e., the time period after the last <termRef>release cycle</termRef> ends to before the next begins.  <termRef term="pre-alpha">Pre-alpha</termRef> activities may include (but are not limited to):  production of <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef> and <termRef term="core supplement">core supplements</termRef>; identification and resolution of <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef>, identification of new requirements, refactorization of NIEM objects, and essentially any other activity that can be performed in a preparatory manner before a <termRef>release cycle</termRef> begins, and recorded into the <termRef>issue tracking area</termRef> and subsequently applied in the next appropriate <termRef>release cycle</termRef>.</p>
	</definition>

	<p><termRef term="pre-alpha">Pre-alpha</termRef> activities significantly reduce the surge activity often perceived or occurring with a <termRef>release cycle</termRef>.  The need for a significant spike in resources during a NIEM <termRef>release cycle</termRef> is generally a myth; most often it is the result of postponement or procrastination of the regular <termRef>pre-alpha</termRef> activities that should always be common practice in <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef>.</p>

</section>



<section id="Exceptions"><title>Release Cycle Exceptions and Options</title>

	<p>Based on history, two <termRef term="minor release">minor releases</termRef> and one <termRef>major release</termRef> in a three-year period (each <termRef>release cycle</termRef> executed annually) will generally accommodate the expected demand for future model changes.  So, by default the appropriate release will always be planned each year without the need for prior approvals.</p>

	<p>There is no desire to force unnecessary releases.  Therefore, as circumstances demand, the NTAC, NBAC, domains, and the PMO may jointly evaluate conditions and elect to adjust the schedule as needed.  Special options include:</p>

	<ul>
		<li><p>Cancel a <termRef>minor release</termRef> (e.g., due to insufficient need for domain and code table changes).</p></li>
		<li><p>Postpone a <termRef>major release</termRef> for a year (e.g., due to insufficient architectural and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> changes).  In this case, the expected <termRef>major release</termRef> may be replaced by a <termRef>minor release</termRef> to accommodate regular <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> and code table changes.</p></li>
		<li><p>Advance a <termRef>major release</termRef> (e.g., due to high priority architectural or <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef> changes).  In this case, the regular <termRef>minor release</termRef> would be cancelled.</p></li>
	</ul>		

</section>

<section id="OutlineThreeYearCycle"><title>Outline of the Three-Year Cycle</title>

	<p><ref idref="ThreeYearCycle"/> illustrates a typical NIEM three-year period.  The following notes explain the activity tracks within the diagram:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><p>Architecture and specifications:  Two years are available to address and prepare for architectural requirements and develop associated specification changes prior to the next <termRef>major release</termRef> during which such changes are applied.</p></li>
		<li><p>Content:  A normal NIEM <termRef>release cycle</termRef> begins with the <termRef>alpha</termRef> stage.  Per this HLVA, whenever NIEM is not executing a major or minor <termRef>release cycle</termRef>, it is in a pre-alpha stage.  Pre-alpha includes adding and resolving content <termRef term="NIEM issue">issues</termRef> in NCCT; preparing <termRef term="domain update">domain updates</termRef>; on-boarding new domains; addressing new requirements; harmonizing content and queuing solutions for the next release; etc.</p></li>
		<li><p>Tools:  After a year, new or changes to existing specifications will enter a more stable <termRef>beta</termRef> stage and can be published for the community review.  Upgrades to reference tools and other capabilities can begin development and finish in time to assist with the next <termRef>major release</termRef>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Training:  Training can begin revision to keep pace with updates to architecture and content.</p></li>
		<li><p>Face-to-face meetings:  Though not shown in this chart, the first semi-annual joint NBAC/NTAC face-to-face meeting can coincide with initial planning (or at least as a key synchronization point) for the <termRef>release cycle</termRef>; the second within a few weeks prior to start of the <termRef>beta</termRef> stage, thus providing a graceful transition from <termRef>alpha</termRef> to <termRef>beta</termRef>.</p></li>
	</ul>

	<figure id="ThreeYearCycle"><title>The NIEM Three Year Cycle.</title>
		<image src="img/ros.png"/>
	</figure>

	<p>Although face-to-face governance meetings are extremely valuable for release planning, coordination, <termRef>harmonization</termRef>, and <termRef term="NIEM issue">issue</termRef> resolution, they are not absolutely necessary.  In the event that face-to-face meetings cannot be held, teleconferences, collaboration tools, and other means will be sufficient to execute a <termRef term="NIEM release">release</termRef>.</p>

</section>
</section>



<section id="Summary"><title>Summary</title>

	<p>Under the NIEM version architecture, <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> are free to publish <termRef term="domain update">updates</termRef> on their own timelines, without being required to wait for <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef> or other <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> to act.  The architecture ensures that all such updates are available for use in IEPDs or other uses of NIEM schema documents.  The architecture ensures that <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> will be available to developers at regularly scheduled intervals, and that those releases will be easy to use, and free of structural inconsistency.</p>

	<p>The version architecture also ensures that domain changes are available in a concrete form that may be incorporated into the next <termRef>NIEM release</termRef>.  It also ensures that <termRef term="NIEM release">NIEM releases</termRef> are scheduled such that they may incorporate recent <termRef term="NIEM domain">domain</termRef> changes.  <termRef>NIEM governance</termRef> has authority to make required modifications in order to ensure consistency between the <termRef term="NIEM domain">domains</termRef> and <termRef term="NIEM core">core</termRef>.</p>

	<p>This document has described the NIEM version architecture at a high level.  The high level description will be expanded and refined into a specification.  The specification will detail the processes, activities and artifacts that are required to maintain high-quality and transparent change management for NIEM.</p>

</section>



<!-- ############## Appendices ############## -->


<section id="Acronyms-and-Abbreviations" isAppendix="true"><title>Acronyms and Abbreviations</title>

<table id="acronyms-abbreviations">

        <theadr>
		<th>Acronym / Abbreviation</th>
		<th>Literal or Definition</th>
	</theadr>

	<tr><td>ESC  </td><td>Executive Steering Council</td></tr>
	<tr><td>HLVA </td><td>High Level Version Architecture</td></tr>
	<tr><td>IEP  </td><td>Information Exchange Package</td></tr>
	<tr><td>IEPD </td><td>Information Exchange Package Documentation</td></tr>
	<tr><td>MPD  </td><td>Model Package Description</td></tr>
	<tr><td>NDR  </td><td>Naming and Design Rules</td></tr>
	<tr><td>NIEM </td><td>National Information Exchange Model</td></tr>
	<tr><td>NBAC </td><td>NIEM Business Architecture Committee</td></tr>
	<tr><td>NCCT </td><td>NIEM Configuration Control Tool</td></tr>
	<tr><td>NTAC </td><td>NIEM Technical Architecture Committee</td></tr>
	<tr><td>PMO  </td><td>Program Management Office</td></tr>
	<tr><td>SSGT </td><td>Schema Subset Generation Tool</td></tr>
	<tr><td>URI  </td><td>Uniform Resource Identifier</td></tr>
	<tr><td>W3C  </td><td>World Wide Web Consortium</td></tr>
	<tr><td>XML  </td><td>Extensible Markup Language</td></tr>
	<tr><td>XSD  </td><td>XML Schema Definition</td></tr>
</table>

	<p> <char name="nbsp"/> </p>
</section>



<section id="References" isAppendix="true"><title>References</title>

<reference id="NIEM-Conformance" label="NIEM Conformance">
	<p><em>NIEM Conformance</em>, Version 3.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), 15 August 2014.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/conformance/3.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-CTAS" label="NIEM Conformance Target Attribute Specification">
	<p><em>NIEM Conformance Targets Attribute Specification</em>, Version 3.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), 31 July 2014.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/conformance-targets-attribute/3.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-DomainUpdate" label="NIEM Domain Update Specification">
	<p><em>NIEM Domain Update Specification</em>, Version 1.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), 5 November 2010.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/domain-update/1.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-HLTA" label="NIEM High-Level Tool Architecture">
	<p><em>NIEM High-Level Tool Architecture</em>, Version 1.1, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee, 1 December 2008.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/high-level-tool-architecture/1.1/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-HLVA1" label="NIEM High-Level Version Architecture v1.0"><p><em>NIEM High Level Version Architecture (HLVA)</em>, Version 1.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee, 31 July 2008.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/high-level-version-architecture/1.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-HLVA3" label="NIEM High-Level Version Architecture v3.0"><p><em>NIEM High Level Version Architecture (HLVA)</em>, Version 3.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee, 27 April 2015.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/high-level-version-architecture/3.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-Implementation" label="NIEM Implementation Guide">
	<p><q>NIEM Implementation Guide</q>, NIEM Program Management Office.  Available from <link>https://www.niem.gov/aboutniem/grant-funding/Pages/implementation-guide.aspx</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-MPD" label="NIEM MPD Specification 3.0.1">
	<p><em>NIEM Model Package Description (MPD) Specification</em>, Version 3.0.1, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), 27 April 2015.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/model-package-description/3.0.1/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-MPD-Toolkit" label="NIEM MPD Toolkit">
	<p><q>NIEM Model Package Description Toolkit</q>, Version 3.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), 15 August 2014.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/resource/mpd/3.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-NDR" label="NIEM NDR">
	<p><em>NIEM Naming and Design Rules (NDR)</em>, Version 3.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), 31 July 2014.  Available from <link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/naming-and-design-rules/3.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="NIEM-QASP" label="NIEM Quality Assurance">
	<p><em>NIEM Quality Assurance Strategy and Plan</em>, Version 1.0, NIEM Technical Architecture Committee (NTAC), 20 May 2008.  Available from
		<link>http://reference.niem.gov/niem/guidance/quality-assurance-strategy-and-plan/1.0/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="PKZIP">
	<p><em>APPNOTE.TXT - .ZIP File Format Specification</em>, Version: 6.3.2, Revised: 28 September 2007, Copyright (c) 1989 - 2007 PKWare Inc.  Available from <link>http://www.pkware.com/documents/casestudies/APPNOTE.TXT</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="RFC2119-KeyWords" label="RFC 2119 Key Words">
	<p>Bradner, S., <em>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</em>, IETF RFC 2119, March 1997.  Available from <link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="RFC3986-URI" label="RFC 3986 URI">
	<p>Berners-Lee, T., et al., <em>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</em>, Request for Comment 3986, Network Working Group, January 2005.  Available from <link>http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3986</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="W3-XML">
	<p><em>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</em>, Version 1.0, Fifth Edition, W3C Recommendation 26 November 2008.  Available from <link>http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="W3-XML-InfoSet">
	<p><em>XML Information Set</em>, Second Edition, W3C Recommendation 4 February 2004.  Available from <link>http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xml-infoset-20040204/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="W3-XML-Namespaces">
	<p><em>Namespaces in XML</em>, Second Edition, World Wide Web Consortium 16 August 2006.  Available from <link>http://www.w3.org/TR/2006/REC-xml-names-20060816/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="W3-XML-Schema-Datatypes" label="W3C XML Schema Datatypes">
	<p><em>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</em>, Second Edition, W3C Recommendation 28 October 2004.  Available from <link>http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/</link>.</p>
</reference>

<reference id="W3-XML-Schema-Structures" label="W3C XML Schema Structures">
	<p><em>XML Schema Part 1: Structures</em>, Second Edition, W3C Recommendation 28 October 2004.  Available from <link>http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-1-20041028/</link>.</p>
</reference>

</section>


<section><title>Index of Definitions</title>
	<indexOfDefinitions/>
</section>

<section id="Revision-History" isAppendix="true"><title>Revision History</title>

	<p>Significant changes in version 3.0 (27 August 2015):</p>
	<ol>
		<li><p>This document is now in HTML format (and text) with highlighted definitions and hyperlinks.</p></li>
		<li><p>Added new <ref idref="Timelines"/> describing the NIEM Release Optimization Strategy approved by the Executive Steering Council (ESC) in June 2014.</p></li>
		<li><p>Revised both <ref idref="incoherent"/> and <ref idref="coherent"/> for clarity.  Text referring to these figures was also (1) revised for clarity, and (2) better synchronized to the figures.</p></li>
		<li><p>All former references to "core update" are now <q><a href="http://reference.niem.gov/niem/specification/high-level-version-architecture/3.0/high-level-version-architecture-3.0.html#definition_core_supplement">core supplement</a></q>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Added to <ref idref="Scope"/> that the HLVA does not address IEPD versioning.  IEPDs are managed and versioned independently of the Core and domains.  In the near term, the PMO will publish guidance for IEPD change control and versioning (through the NIEM Technical Architecture Committee).</p></li>
	</ol>

</section>

</document>

